What comes to mind
提到土耳其
when you think of Türkiye
你能想到什么
tourist attraction
是旅游胜地
Ottoman Empire
奥斯曼帝国
Turkey
火鸡
or Salt Bae
还是撒盐哥
Let me tell you this
不过我跟你说
the strangest thing about Türkiye
土耳其最奇葩的地方
is their economy
是它的经济
In 2022
2022年
Türkiye's inflation rate
土耳其的通货膨胀率
suddenly began to soar above 80%
突然开始飙升到超过80%
Value of Turkish lira dropped by half in a year
土耳其里拉一年之内跌了一半
Sounds very bad
这听着挺惨的
But in 2022
可是人家2022年
Their GDP growth was at 5.6%
好像GDP逆势增长了5.6%
The entire stock market increased by three folds
整个股市更是翻了三倍
Moreover, their President
更奇葩的是他的总统老先生
has been dissing on interest rate non-stop
整天怼天怼地怼利率
saying interest rate is evil
说利率就是恶魔
We need to believe in one true God
我们要相信真主安拉
A big country
一个拥有
of 85 million people
8500万人口的大国
Its GDP ranks among the world's top 20
GDP排名世界前20
Going against mainstream economics
竟然跟主流经济学对着干
Trump even said he will
特朗普都已经说
destroy Türkiye’s economy
要摧毁土耳其经济了
but he is unequivocal and put on tough stand
但是他毫不含糊 还正面硬刚
What are all this about？
这一切到底是怎么回事呢
Let’s get into it with Lin
咱们快来跟小Lin一起
and discover the eccentricity
了解一下这个奇葩的
of Turkish Economy
土耳其经济
Let's start with a very quick background
首先咱们先非常快速地
on the Turkish economy
了解一下土耳其经济的背景
In the early days
其实早期
Türkiye had been relatively closed
土耳其一直都比较封闭
they were just doing their own thing
就自己慢慢悠悠发展自己的
However after WWII
可是二战之后
Looking at Europe in the north, huddled together for warmth
就眼瞅着北边的欧洲抱团取暖
The development was in full swing
发展得是如火如荼
Turkey wanted to join too
土耳其心里也痒痒
and had applied many times
三番五次要申请
to join the predecessor of EU
加入欧盟的前身
They even opened their country wide
并且还把自己的国门大敞开
to allow western capitalists
允许西方资本
to invest in Türkiye
到土耳其来进行投资
but they opened up too fast too wide
结果一下放太开 没把持住
ended up owing huge amount of debt
土耳其政府就欠了一屁股外债
The only solution then was
只能出下策
to keep printing money
就是不停地印钱
and exchange it into USD to pay off the debt
然后换成美元去还债
Moreover in the 80s
再加上80年代
the two oil crises
两次石油危机的冲击
had kept inflation high in Türkiye
就让土耳其这个通胀居高不下
It had reached more than 120% several times
好几次都冲到了120%以上
With just few short sentences
你别看咱们短短几句
we’ve already pointed
说土耳其的历史
to two main problems
已经点到了土耳其经济的
in Turkish economy
两大核心问题
external debt and inflation
就是外债和通胀
The Turkish government realised that
土耳其政府慢慢就意识到
NO
说不行
we can’t go down like this
我不能再这么堕落下去了
else the gap between us and the EU
这样我会跟欧洲的差距
will grow wider
拉得越来越大
So from 1999
于是从1999年开始
Türkiye firmly caried out
土耳其就真的非常坚决地
a series of reforms
进行了一系列的改革
One of the most important task
这里边最重要的一点
was to completely separate
就是把央行
central bank from the government
从政府给完全分离出来了
This is
而这一点
of absolute important
在当代的经济体当中
in contemporary economy bodies
是非常重要的
This is because the power of
因为央行的权力
central bank is too big
它实在是太大了
where they could print money and control interest rate
又能印钱 又能控制利率
Imagine
你想
if the government make all the decisions
它要是什么都政府说了算的话
It could lead to
那就非常有可能
the bank becoming government’s
发展成政府自己家后院的
personal money printing machine
一个印钞机
Even if the government is very determined
就算你政府非常有定力
but the market was still worried
但市场还是担心
so they wouldn’t dare to
大家就不能放开了手脚
invest or trade
给你投资或者给你进行贸易
The Turkish government
所以土耳其政府
had to no matter what
只能一咬牙 一跺脚
separate from the central bank
就把这个摇钱树给独立出去了
Once become independent
独立出去之后
if the government were to issue debt
政府这边如果要发债
it has to follow the supply and demand of the market.
那就得遵循市场的供需了
If the market feels that your default risk
市场如果觉得你的违约风险
or future inflation expectations are high
或者是未来通胀预期很高的话
the price of government bonds
国债的价格在拍卖的时候
will be lowered
就会压得很低
This invisibly
就无形之间
put great pressure on the government
给了政府很大的压力
The government has to control
就是你必须得控制好
national finance
自己国家的财政
as well as inflation
还有通货膨胀
For the next few years, the Turkish government
土耳其政府在接下来的几年里
started to cut expenditures
就节衣缩食 削减开支
and pushed the debt-to-GDP ratio
把债务比GDP这个比例
down to 30%
愣是给压到了30%
You have to know that
你要知道
it is considered to be healthy
这个比例要在50%以下
if the ratio is below 50%
就已经算是非常非常健康了
Let’s not look at the crazy ones
咱都不说像美国 日本
like USA and Japan
这种非常狂野的
Even the very restrained German government
就非常克制的德国政府
has almost never gone down below 60%
这个比例都(几乎)没下过60%
So you can imagine
所以你可想而知
this 30% is very
土耳其这个30%
impressive for Türkiye
是非常厉害的
They also liberalized financial controls
同时他也放开了金融管制
let the lira float to adjust to supply and demand
让里拉自由浮动来调整供需
To curb high inflation
为了压制住高通胀
they even increase the
甚至疯狂地
interest rate to 100%
把利率加到了100%
Türkiye completely changed
你看看人家这土耳其的表现
turned over new leaf
可以说是一改往日的浪子形象
and trying to be a better nation
洗心革面重新做国
So what’s the result?
那结果怎么样呢
It crashed
崩了
The Turkish lira has lost more than
土耳其里拉在8个月内
half its value in eight months
疯狂缩水了一半多
This was not that bad
其实还好了
This is only a brief period of pain
这个只是汇率放开之后
after the exchange rate liberalization
短暂的一个阵痛期
Turkish Lira did crash for awhile
土耳其里拉确实崩了一下
but managed to be controlled
但就控制住了
Inflation was being pressed down
通胀也非常迅猛的
very rapidly
就被按下来了
That's 100% interest rate
你想那可是100%的利率
It’s not just inflation
你别说通货膨胀了
anything that would inflate will be pressed down
谁膨胀 我都能给你摁瘪了
Before this Turkish Lira
同时因为土耳其里拉
depreciated too much
它之前贬值实在是太厉害了
had to spend thousands of lira
就是你出去吃个饭
just for a meal
就得花几千万里拉
it had disrupted
实在是有点搞笑
normal operation of the economy
都已经阻碍正常的经济运行了
Therefore in 2005
于是土耳其
Türkiye
就在2005年的时候
introduced a new lira
推出了一个新里拉
New Turkish Lira
就一新土耳其里拉
A meal that cost a million lira before
等于原来100万里拉
now is just
你看这下你吃一顿饭
about 10 lira
就十几里拉就可以了
With the new currency
好 这下货币也用上新的了
it marks that Türkiye had
你看土耳其就经过了
manage to transform itself completely
彻头彻尾的一段改革之后
and ready for the new spring
就迎来了自己的春天
A large influx of external investment
大量外部投资涌入
boosted the Turkish economy
全面带动了土耳其经济
From 2001 until 2016
从2001到2016年间
except slightly impacted during
除了金融危机那会儿
the financial crisis period
受到了一点小的冲击
the GDP growth
其他年份每年的GDP增长率
was kept at 5% to 12%
都保持在5%到12%之间
With the inflation being
你看这个通货膨胀率
pressed down so low
神奇般地被压得这么低
Turkey's heavy industry, textile industry
土耳其的重工业 纺织业
agriculture, etc. are all rising rapidly
农业等等都快速崛起
Exports have increased sixfold in eight years
出口额在八年之间翻了六倍
Tourism has grown even more
旅游业发展得就更猛了
In 2019, it became
2019年成为了
the sixth most visited country in the world
全球游客排名第六的国家
It brings more than $30 billion
每年都会给土耳其带来
in revenue to Türkiye every year
三百多亿美元的收入
However
不过
behind the Turkish spring
就在这个土耳其春天的背后
there are two major problems
隐隐的有那么两大问题
One is account deficit
一个就是他经常账户赤字
or trade deficit
或者说贸易逆差
Imports consistently outnumber exports
就进口持续性地大于出口
Meaning the goods that you buy
也就是说你买的东西
is consistently more than the goods that you sell
持续性地要多于你卖的东西
Türkiye is already
土耳其几乎已经是
one of the countries that’s
全球经常账户赤字里边
with the most deficit in the world
最多的国家之一了
So you have to keep spending money right
那你就一直在花钱 对吧
and you need USD or Euro to import
你就得花美元 花欧元去进口
now the problem comes
那问题就来了
Where would Türkiye get
你说土耳其
so much USD or Euro
是哪来那么多美元 欧元
to support trade deficit?
去支持它这个贸易逆差呢
This happened to lead to the second problem
这个恰恰就是它的第二大问题
external debt
就是外债
We mentioned earlier that
我们之前不是说
As government debt continues to fall
它政府债务是持续下降的嘛
private debt continues to rise
那和政府债务形成对比的
in contrast to government debt
就是他私人的债务持续攀升
Actually the increase in personal loans
其实本来 个人贷款增加
is not a bad thing
并不是什么坏事
It is what modern economies would like to see
反而是当代经济体愿意看到的
Because borrowing money means
因为你借钱
your investment needs
就说明你的投资需求
and consumption needs is robust
消费需求都比较旺盛
But Türkiye is borrowing from external source
但是土耳其借的是外债
that is Euro, GBP, USD
就是欧元 英镑 美元
it’s not lira
它就不是里拉
In other word, you can’t print the money
换句话说 你就没法自己印
At that time Türkiye
因为土耳其当时
wanted to join EU
不是想抱欧盟的大腿
so they opened up their country
就把自己的国门敞得非常开
It was very easy
那民众想去借点外债
for their citizens to get foreign loan
是非常容易的
For Turkish entrepreneurs
对于土耳其这些企业来讲
inflation and interest rate is very low
你看 外边欧元 美元
for Euro and USD
通货膨胀又低 利率还低
so they were very inclined
所以他们就非常倾向于
to take up foreign loan
去借这个外债
By 2019
到2019年的时候
within Turkish citizens’ savings
土耳其的居民储蓄里边
50% of them is in
已经有超过50%
foreign currency
都是以外币的形式
Can you imagine
好家伙 你敢想象吗
that for half of the country, the money saved is not in lira
就半个国家存的钱都不是里拉
A new noun created for this
这个也产生了一个专有名词
Dollarization
叫美元化 Dollarization
the word Dollar in here
这里的这个Dollar
refers to all foreign currency
它是泛指所有的外币
The problem is easy to understand
这个问题就很好理解了
It’s not a very bad thing
你一个国家的居民
for the citizens of a country
去借大量的外债
to get foreign loan extensively
倒也不是说不行
but when they couldn’t pay
但是一旦他还不上
that’s where the trouble comes
出问题的时候
that affect the country
就国家就很麻烦了
The trouble came
这麻烦它说来就来了
in 2014
2014年
Türkiye had a new president
土耳其上任了一位新总统
key figures in Türkiye
也是土耳其的关键人物
his name is Recep Tayyip Erdogan
他叫埃尔多安
Actually from 2003
其实他从2003年开始
he was already the Prime Minister
就已经是土耳其的总理了
The prosperity of Türkiye
这土耳其的繁荣
has a lot to do with him
也跟他有不小的关系
so he was very popular back then
所以他的呼声是非常高的
Once he became President
这下当了总统之后
he took Türkiye on a
把土耳其那是带上了
very eccentric path
不能叫不归路吧
Although before
虽然之前
Türkiye was growing very fast and very well
土耳其都发展得很快 很好
but because
但是因为
of its severe trade deficit
它贸易逆差非常严重了
the market
所以市场
was worried about dollar shortage
就会担心它出现美元荒
similar to last year’s Sri Lanka
就有点像去年斯里兰卡那样
causing Turkish lira to fall
土耳其里拉就开始持续下跌
Later Türkiye bought a few
后来土耳其又从俄罗斯
fighter jets from Russia
买了一些战斗机
Türkiye is a NATO member
你想 土耳其可是北约的成员
the act of buying fighter jets from Russia
他跟俄罗斯买战斗机
pissed off USA
那这一下可就把美国给惹毛了
Trump started attacking him
特朗普就开始对他进行炮轰
and said
就说
if you don’t control yourself
你们要是不好好管管你们自己
I’ll destroy
我就要彻彻底底地
Turkish economy
摧毁土耳其的经济
I’m not embellishing the story
这可不是我添油加醋
this comes from his Twitter
这是他推特上发的原话
He also imposed punitive tariffs
他还给土耳其的原材料
on Turkish raw materials
加了惩罚性的关税
Erdogan is ruthless yet talkative
那埃尔多安也是人狠话又多
and he isn’t scared of Trump
一点都不怵特朗普
He even go around
还激情澎湃
the country to give speech passionately
就在国内发表演讲说
Just ignore the USA,  they have dollars
不要管他们美国 他们有美元
We have the people
我们有人民
We have God
我们有真主
We have Allah
我们有阿拉
Sounds inspiring right
是不是还挺燃的
regardless, market was freaked out
燃归燃 可市场是真的吓尿了
They were already worried
本来就担心
of the dollar shortage in Türkiye
土耳其这边的美元荒
and now the fight with USA
好 你跟美国还掐起来了
Due to this situation
看着这架势
international capital all fled away
国际资本就一窝蜂地全吓跑了
From 2018 till 2019
2018到2019一年之间
nearly half of foreign capital withdrew from the market
外国的资本撤了将近一半
Turkish Lira almost collapse
土耳其里拉更是一泻千里
Don’t forget we mentioned earlier that
你别忘了 咱刚刚说
Turkish citizens borrowed a lot of foreign loan
土耳其民间是借了大量的外债
if foreign capital withdraw overnight
外资要是一夜之间全撤光的话
then the capital chain for both
那土耳其这边个人和公司
personal and companies might be broken
很可能资金链就要断
With the rapid depreciation of the lira
而且随着里拉的快速贬值
The inflation that has been gone
土耳其这边已经几乎消失
for almost 10 years in Turkey
快十年的通货膨胀
is making a comeback
也又开始抬头了
In the face of crisis, the Turkish central bank
面对这种危机 土耳其央行
did a standard procedure very decisively
非常果决的做了一个标准流程
and that is increase interest rate
就是加息
Higher interest rates can curb inflation
加息可以抑制通胀
drag down the local exchange rate
而且还能拖住本地的汇率
This is a good thing
这个好
I’ve talked about this extensively in the inflation episode
我在通胀那期详细地聊过
With this, the inflation in Türkiye
所以土耳其的通胀
managed to be pressed down
也就顺顺利利被摁下来了
However President Erdogan
但是 埃尔多安老先生
came out and said
这时候又跳出来了
no we should not increase interest rate
不 我们不应该加息
we should decrease it
应该降息
interest rate is mother and father all evils
利率是mother and father all evils
mother and father of all evils
就是所有恶魔的父亲和母亲
What economists say in other countries around the world
全世界别的国家经济学家说的
is bullshit and wrong
都是扯淡 都不对
Only by cutting interest rates can curb inflation
降息才可以抑制通胀
You must be wondering what is he thinking
您是不是好奇他是怎么想的
If he wasn’t crazy
如果他不是脑子进水的话
We’ll analyse this later
这个咱们一会慢慢分析
Anyhow, Erdogan
反正就埃尔多安
forcefully urged the central bank to cut interest rates
强硬地要求央行降息
The governor of central bank is an economist after all
央行行长怎么着也是经济学者
Mr President this is ridiculous
总统先生 您这个也太扯了吧
how can we cut interest rate during high inflation
高通胀的时候怎么能降息呢
didn’t you watch Lin’s video?
你是不是没看过小Lin视频
We said earlier that
我们之前不是说
the government separated
政府不好不容易
the central bank from the government
把央行从政府里边独立出去了
Technically
也就是说理论上
they don’t have to listen to Erdogan
它可以不需要听埃尔多安的话
However
可是
Erdogan was well prepared
这个埃尔多安是早有准备
In 2017
他在2017年的时候
he amended the constitution
就修改了宪法
so that he could possess
让自己拥有了
the right to appoint central bankers
任命央行官员的这个权利
So are you going to cut the rate?
你就说降不降吧
No? Alright
不降 是吧
Your day as governor is over
那央行行长你也别做了
he removed the governor of the central bank
2019年把央行行长给开了
And replaced with someone who would listen to him
然后换上来个听话的
Immediate interest cut
Hello
Imagine
那你想
when the market see such a weird President
市场看到一个如此奇怪的总统
they got even more panic and withdraw from the market
就更慌了 疯狂撤离
Lira dropped again
里拉又开始迅速下跌
The new governor
这个新行长
upon seeing the condition of Lira
看里拉实在是止不住了
started to increase the rate again
就又开始加息
but he was sacked
结果又被开了
The new governor
又新上来一个
had to increase the interest rate a few days later
没过两天也不得不加息
and got sacked again
结果又被开了
Just like this
就这样
three governors of Turkish Central Bank
堂堂的土耳其央行行长
was sacked in the period of 2 years
两年之内被开了仨
The new governor is simple
再新上来一个 那可老实了
you want it cut, then we’ll cut the rates
你说降 那咱就降
This means that
这也意味着
an independent central bank system
就土耳其好不容易建立起来的
that was built before
央行独立的这个机制
was broken by Erdogan
已经被埃尔多安给打破
Even the former Prime Minister
就连土耳其的前总理
Erdogan's former number two person
也就是埃尔多安原来的二把手
openly said that
都公开说
Erdogan doesn’t understand economy
说埃尔多安不懂经济
the people around him also don’t understand economy
他身边的人也都不懂经济
He is like from another planet
他就像从另一个宇宙来的一样
See
你看
even the criticism sound civilized
是不是骂人骂得还挺文明的
So now let’s see
好 那我们来看看
what exactly is in the mind of
这个埃尔多安老先生
President Erdogan
他是怎么想的
Of course I couldn’t possibly now
当然我不可能知道
his exact thoughts
他具体真实是怎么想的
I could only base it from
我只能通过
some of his speeches, interviews
他的一些演讲 采访
or public information
或者公开的一些资料
to understand
来看到一些依据
He actually has a
其实他是有自己一套
perfect logic chain
非常完整的逻辑链条
Aren't you all going to talk about economics?
你们不是要讲经济学吗
Alright
来
Let me tell you my economics
我给你们讲一讲我的经济学
By cutting interest rate, we can drive
你看 降息就可以带动
demand and investment growth
需求和投资的增长吧
When demand and investment grow
那需求跟投资增长了
it could drive the increase of commodity
不就可以带动商品的增加吗
If the increase in the supply of a commodity
商品供给的增加
is higher than the increase in demand
如果它高于需求的增加
won't the price drop?
那价格不就降下来了吗
This not only could curb inflation
这样既控制住了通胀
and can keep growth
还保住了增长
Actually what he said
其实他说的这些
you can’t say it’s not making sense
你也不能说完全没有道理
It’s just that from past experience
只是就是一般经验表明
the negative impact of low interest rate
低利率带来的负面效果
is often bigger than
也远远大于
the positive impact that he mentioned
他说的这些正面效果
Low interest rates can cause the economy to overheat
低利率会导致经济过热
the effect of increased demand will be more  distinct
需求增加的效果会更明显
which will cause higher inflation rate
它就会导致更高的通货膨胀
You might be a bit confuse now
这么秃噜秃噜你可能有点懵
Let me give you an example
来 我来给你举一个
it’s not necessarily a good metaphor
不一定很恰当的比喻
This is like
这就好比
a car that is moving very fast
有一个滑得很快的小车
and you want it to stop
你想让它停下来
people would normally think to pull it
那正常人肯定觉得你应该拉它
but for Erdogan
但埃尔多安说了
he said no you shouldn’t pull it
说 不 你不应该拉它
you should push it
你应该推它
because when you push it
因为当你推它的时候
it’ll move faster
它会滑得更快
and it’ll create a bigger
这样就会产生更大的
air resistance and friction
空气阻力和摩擦力
when these two forces is
当这两个力
bigger than the thrust
大于你的推力的时候
the speed will slow down
它的速度就会慢下来
So if you want it to slow down
所以说如果你想让它慢下来
you shouldn’t pull it, you should push it instead
你不应该拉它 而应该推它
Of course economics
当然 经济学
is definitely not as absolute as physics
肯定不会像物理那么绝对
Let me make an example
我就举个例子
so you can feel it
让大家可以直观地感受一下
After listening to this
这个比喻这么一听
you must think
你是不是就觉得
this man must have no common sense
这个人肯定一点常识也没有
Actually in the economy world
其实就是经济学界
that’s how people view him
看埃尔多安也是这么个感觉
According to Erdogan’s theory
要是按照埃尔多安的理论
you cut the rate when the economy is overheated
就是经济过热的时候 你降息
you also cut the rate to stimulate economy
刺激经济你也降息
This is Erdogan’s target
还真的就是埃尔多安的目标
No matter how bad the inflation
就我不管通胀是多少
I’m going to lower the interest rate to 0
我就是要把利率降到零
Then why must he
那他为什么
lower the interest rate down to zero?
想把利率非要降到零呢
This is because of his religious belief
其实是因为他的宗教信仰
Türkiye is an Islamic nation
土耳其是一个伊斯兰大国
And the teachings of Islam emphasize that
而伊斯兰教的教义就强调了
interest rate is bad
说利率这个东西它是罪恶的
you shouldn’t use money to make profit
就是你不应该用金钱去牟利
That’s why Erdogan said
所以才有埃尔多安说
interest rate is the father and mother of all evils
利率是恶魔的父母
Due to this teaching
也是因为这个教义
It’s very difficult for the
就在土耳其的银行业
banking industry in Türkiye
是非常难做
Whatever they do is not justified properly
就你搞什么都名不正言不顺的
have to figure out various ways
整天就得想着各种方法
to go around this evil interest rate
来绕过这个罪恶的利率
If you were
你比如说
to buy a house in Türkiye via loan
要是在土耳其你想贷款买房
then the bank can’t charge you interest
那银行是不能收你利息的
They have to buy this house
它先得花钱把这个房子买下来
and sell it to you at a higher price
然后再高价地卖给你
and loan it to you with zero interest
然后给你零息贷款
or they rent the house to you
或者就直接把这个房子租给你
Well they can adjust the rental
那这个月租不就可以再调了嘛
Anyway they think of everything they could
反正就是想尽一切办法
to get around interest rate
把利率这个事儿给绕过去
From here you can see that
你也可以看出来
the Turkish is very much against
土耳其人真的是非常排斥
interest rate
利率这个事儿
Back to the story
好 我们说回来
Erdogan wanted to cut the interest rate
埃尔多安不是非要降息吗
What is the result
那他这个反常规的操作
of his unconventional operation?
结果怎么样呢
Erdogan was unfortunate
也算是埃尔多安倒霉
got caught up with the 2022 energy crisis
赶上了2022年的能源危机
That has left Türkiye
这就让土耳其
a big energy importer
这个能源进口大国
reeling
彻底吃不消了
You see
你看
This is the inflation rate of Türkiye
这个是土耳其的通货膨胀率
in half year
半年之内
from 20% surge up to 80%
从20%一下飙升到了80%
And this is official data
而且这个还是官方数据
According to private estimation
就各种民间估算
this number should be about
这个数字应该在
100% to 200%
100%到200%之间
Foreign capital fled in panic again
外资就又恐慌性地撤离
The lira halved in yet another year
里拉就又一年之内跌了一半
Turkish citizens if they have
土耳其本国人
money in hand that can be exchanged into foreign currency
他手里的钱要是能换成外币
they did it quickly
那赶紧换
If they don’t then it’ll be worthless
换不成就难了
because the deposit interest rate is very low
你想要是存银行利率那么低
and inflation is high
通胀那么高 那谁还去存银行
With money on hand, people started to spend it
所以大家拿着钱就去开始消费
by stocking up goods, buy houses, stocks
存货 买房子 买股票
In 2022
你看 这2022年
Türkiye's domestic consumption is booming
土耳其国内是消费蹿得
The stock market is the best in the world
股市更是全球之最
See
你看
every other country has fallen so hard
各个其他国家都跌得那么惨
meanwhile Türkiye’s figure is 300%
土耳其暴涨了300%
Strong consumption and investment
这么强的消费和投资
indeed drives
也确实带动了
very strong GDP
2021年和2022年
in 2021 and 2022
土耳其非常强劲的GDP
Even if the global economy is weak
即使全球经济疲软
Even if the energy crisis hits hard
即使能源危机打击巨大
In 2022
2022年
Türkiye manage to keep
土耳其依旧保持了
growth of 5.6%
5.6%的增长率
Consumption is good
你一看 这消费也挺好的
Stock market is doing well, GDP is growing as well
股市也挺好的 GDP也在增长
Everything is going well
这不挺好的吗
So what Erdogan said was right
那埃尔多安说得不也挺对的吗
Interest rate cuts really boost consumption
降息真的就带动了消费
It drives investment and exports
带动了投资 带动了出口
These are right
这些也都没错
but it’s only one façade of the economy
但这只是经济的一面
If you ask Turkish citizens
你要是去问土耳其的民众
Few people will tell you
几乎没有人会告诉你
they feel richer
他感觉自己更有钱了
or feel happier
或者生活更幸福了
This prosperity
这种繁荣
can only be counted as
它可能只能算作一种
False prosperity
虚假的繁荣
Actually everyone
其实大家
was in panic spending mode
更多的是恐慌性的消费
or panic buying stocks mode
或者恐慌性的买股票
They spend and invest
而不是因为我对未来更有信心
not because of their confidence in future
而去消费和投资
Although GDP goes up
虽然GDP上去了
but everyone is anxious
可是大家都慌得要死
This prosperity won’t last long
这个是没法持续多久的
One more thing
而且还有一点
the richer families and companies in Türkiye
就土耳其它富裕的家庭和企业
could indeed exchange their money to foreign currency
确实可以把钱换成外汇
or invest their money to avoid inflation
或者去投资来规避通胀
But it’s not the case for lower income group
但是低收入人群可就没辙了
They could only watch their money
你就只能看着自己手里的钱
getting less day-by-day
一点点变少
The rate of salary increase
工资增长的速度
could not keep up with inflation hike
可远远没有通胀涨得那么快
which caused wider gap between rich and poor
就更加加大了贫富差距
More than half of Turkish are actually
现在土耳其有将近一半的人
getting paid the lowest salary
其实都拿着最低工资
Look here
而且你看
This is a demographic chart of Turkey
这个是土耳其的人口结构图
Under 45 years old.. abundant of them
45岁以下 那是多么的雄厚
What an ideal
这个结构图
demographic structure for these aging countries
你要让这些老龄化国家看着
to look at
那是多么的理想
With Erdogan making such a kerfuffle
现在埃尔多安这么一顿折腾
Every year, 300,000 young people
每年都有30万的年轻人
are lost to other countries
要流失到其他国家去
That's 300,000
这可都是
highly educated young people
受过高等教育的30万年轻人
Statistics from a German company show that
有个德国公司的统计就显示
In Türkiye, 73% of young people
土耳其有73%的年轻人
want to leave the country
都希望离开土耳其发展
This loss of talent and confidence
这种人才的流失和信心的流失
will have a bigger
对土耳其长期的影响
long-term impact on Türkiye
我感觉才是更大的
In the face of widespread complaints about inflation
面对这么严重的通胀怨声载道
Erdogan
埃尔多安
didn’t just sit and do nothing
他可不光是就在那坐以待毙的
Other than cutting interest rate
其实他除了非要降息之外
the overall strategy is actually quite clear
整体的策略都还是挺清晰的
He knows that
他知道
Now Türkiye's biggest problem
现在土耳其最严重的问题
is capital outflow
其实是资本外流
If he doesn’t take any measures
我要再不采取措施
the Turkish citizens are going to exchange their currency
那土耳其人都换成外汇了
then it’ll be bad news
那还了得
Moreover for him personally
而且对他个人来讲
the most important for him is Presidential election
很重要的是在2023年6月
in this coming June 2023
就要土耳其进行总统大选了
This is related to whether
这个就关乎到
he can continue to be re-elected.
他能不能继续连任
So Erdogan did two things
所以埃尔多安就干了两件事儿
The first measure is to prevent capital outflows
第一招就是防止资本外流
As an incentive for people to switch back to Lira
为了激励大家能够换回里拉
Other than taking measure
土耳其除了一些基本的
like limiting banks' foreign exchange holdings
限制银行的外汇持有比例等等
They even
这些措施以外
came out with a very creative
还非常想象力地推出一种新的
protected foreign exchange deposit model
受到外汇保护的存款模式
What does it mean?
这是什么意思呢
For those holding USD
就对于那些手里有美元的人
if you exchange USD to Lira
如果你把美元换成里拉
Even after the exchange rate you lose money
那即使在汇率上之后你亏了
Take the collapse of the lira
就比如说里拉暴跌
The bank will pay you back what you lost
你亏多少银行给你补多少
In other words
换句话说
The bank is taking on the exchange rate risk for you
就是银行替你承担了汇率风险
Sounds creative and innovative
这是不是听着还挺有创意的
Erdogan’s second move is
埃尔多安用的第二招
bring in foreign capital
就是去拉拢外部的资本进入
or draw foreign allies
或者就叫拉拢外部同盟
Actually the inflation was
其实你看 土耳其为什么
so high last year in Türkiye
去年通胀那么厉害
including the constant trade deficit
包括一直以来都是贸易逆差
the main reason
很主要一个原因
is because it is
就是因为他是一个
huge energy importer
巨大的能源进口国
Türkiye is quite unlucky
他其实也是不太走运
the geographical area
你看 他这个地理位置
at north there’s Russia, at south there’s Middle East
北边是俄罗斯 南边是中东
All producer of fossil fuels
全都是化石能源 富得流油
But Türkiye
可偏偏就这土耳其
doesn’t really have fossil fuels
就没什么化石能源
90% of their energy has to be imported
他90%能源都得靠进口
This time Erdogan
埃尔多安这回
realised the importance of energy
也是意识到了能源的重要性
He changed his bold and brazen personality
一改往日那个怼天怼地的性格
and started to create
开始跟这些能源大国
good relations with these energy powerhouse
搞好关系了
Although Türkiye is part of NATO
虽说他是北约的成员
but Erdogan is against sanction on Russia
但他就反对西方制裁俄罗斯
He even actively trade with Russia
还积极地跟俄罗斯进行贸易
After Russia-Ukraine war
就俄乌战争之后
the trade between Türkiye and Russia
他跟俄罗斯之间的贸易
increased compared to before war
反倒比战前还多了
He even managed to get
也成功地从俄罗斯那
$9.1 billion
拉到了91亿美元
to build their own nuclear power plant
来建自己的新核电站
Apart from that, Erdogan
另外 埃尔多安
is cuddling up with UAE
还一下子跟阿联酋称兄道弟了
FYI
你要知道
In 2016, Erdogan
埃尔多安在2016年
went through
他经历了一场
a very big military coup
非常大的军事政变
And the big benefactor behind this coup
而这个政变背后的一大金主
is UAE
就是阿联酋
So Erdogan and UAE
所以埃尔多安跟阿联酋
they didn’t get along
那是水火不相容的
This time, he forget the past
这时候可以不计前嫌了
and signed a
两边还签了一个
$4.9 billion currency swap agreement
49亿美元的互换协议
Another is President of Egypt Abdel Fattah al-Sisi
还有就是埃及总统塞西
Before this
之前
Erdogan claimed that he is a murderer
埃尔多安还骂人家是杀人犯
that he is barbaric
骂人家野蛮
This time taking advantage of World Cup
这回趁着世界杯
they held hand
俩人还握上手了
Apart from that, Türkiye got a loan
另外 土耳其还从他的老朋友
from their old friend Qatar
卡塔尔那边
of about $10 billion
拿了100亿美元的贷款
They got $5 billion from Saudi
从沙特那拿了50亿美元
In just a year
这才短短一年
Erdogan
埃尔多安
has become friends with
就跟之前他看不上那些国家
countries he once despised
都成好哥们儿
He also draws in tens of billions of dollars in investment
也拉来了几百亿美元的投资
And you see
而且你看
these countries are energy powerhouse
这些国家可都是能源大户
They have to rely
那咱以后能源进口
on these new friends
不都还指着这些
for energy import
刚结交的新哥们儿嘛
I can only say there’s no eternal enemy
我只能说 没有永远的敌人
only perpetual benefits
只有永远的利益
In February 6th 2023
2023年2月6日
Türkiye suffered two consecutive earthquakes
土耳其连续遭受了两次
with a magnitude of 7.8
高达7.8级的大地震
At least 45,000 people were killed
至少有45000人丧生
Turkish government
土耳其政府
need to spend at least $80 billion
至少需要花800亿美元
to repair the damage
来修复
This will have a huge impact
这个不管是对民众的信心
on public confidence
政府的债务 还有通货膨胀
government debt and inflation
都将会带来巨大的冲击
As for President Erdogan
至于他
will he be able to curb inflation
到底能不能控制住通货膨胀呢
or will Türkiye become Venezuela
还是会像委内瑞拉
or Argentina
或者阿根廷那样的
Will Erdogan be re-elected
埃尔多安他能不能连任成功呢
I
我
do not know
不知道
Only time will tell
只能让时间来告诉咱们答案了